{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "4.2","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["A2 antigen will not react with anti-A, A1 will react strongly (4+)","An A2 person may form anti-A1; an A1 person will not form anti-A1","An A1 person may form anti-A2, an A2 person will not form anti-A1","A2 antigen will not react with anti-A from a nonimmunized donor; A1 will react with any anti-A"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "An A2 person may form anti-A1; an A1 person will not form anti-A1","explanation": "The group A1 comprises both A1 and A antigens. Anti-A will react with both A1- and A2-positive RBCs. A person who is group A2 may form anti-A1, but an A1 person will not form anti-A1 (which would cause autoagglutination)."},"question": "Which of the following distinguishes the A1 blood group from the A2 blood group?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/ABO blood group/2"},{"choices": ["The patient may be a subgroup of A","The patient may have an immunodeficiency","The patient may be a Bombay phenotype individual","The patient may have developed alloantibodies"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The patient may be a Bombay phenotype individual","explanation": "Bombay phenotype is the only ABO phenotype incompatible with O cells. The RBCs of a Bombay phenotype individual show a negative reaction to anti-H because the cells contain no H substance."},"question": "A patient’s serum is incompatible with O cells. The patient RBCs give a negative reaction to anti-H lectin. What is the most likely cause of these results?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/ABO blood group/3"},{"choices": ["Anti-A and anti-B","Anti-H","Anti-A,B","Anti-A, B, and H"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-A, B, and H","explanation": "A Bombay phenotype individual does not express A, B, or H antigens; therefore, anti-A, -B, and -H are formed. Because a Bombay phenotype individual has three antibodies, the only compatible blood must be from another Bombay phenotype donor."},"question": "What antibodies are formed by a Bombay phenotype individual?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/ABO blood group/Bombay/1"},{"choices": ["Bombay phenotype individuals","Group O persons","Persons of all blood groups","Group A persons"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Group A persons","explanation": "The acquired B phenomenon is only seen in group A persons."},"question": "Acquired B antigens have been found in:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental characteristics/ABO/1"},{"choices": ["The patient has an antibody to a low-frequency antigen","The patient has an antibody to a high-frequency antigen","The patient is an A2 with anti-A1","The patient is an A1 with anti-A2"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The patient is an A2 with anti-A1","explanation": "The patient is likely an A2 with anti-A1, which is causing reactivity in the crossmatching. A negative antibody screen rules out the possibility of an antibody to a high-frequency antigen, and two donor units incompatible rules out an antibody to a low-frequency antigen."},"question": "Blood is crossmatched on an A-positive person with a negative antibody screen. The patient received a transfusion of A-positive RBCs 3 years ago. The donors chosen for crossmatching were A-positive. Crossmatching was run on the automated analyzer and yielded 3+ incompatibility. How can these results be explained?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/ABO/3"},{"choices": ["Extend reverse typing for 15 minutes","Perform an antibody screen, including room-temperature incubation","Incubate washed RBCs with anti-A1 and anti-A,B for 30 minutes at room temperature","Test patient’s RBCs with Dolichos biflorus"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Incubate washed RBCs with anti-A1 and anti-A,B for 30 minutes at room temperature","explanation": "The strong 4+ reaction in reverse grouping suggests the discrepancy is in forward grouping. Incubating washed RBCs at room temperature with anti-A and anti-A,B will enhance reactions."},"question": "A patient’s RBCs forward as group O, serum agglutinates B cells (4+) only. Your next step would be:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/RBCs/ABO discrepancy/3"},{"choices": ["Anti-A 4+, anti-B-3+, A1 cells neg, B cells neg","Anti-A 3+, anti-B neg, A1 cells neg, B cells neg","Anti-A 4+, anti-B 1+, A1 cells neg, B cells 4+","Anti-A 4+, anti-B 4+, A1 cells 2+, B cells neg"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-A 4+, anti-B 1+, A1 cells neg, B cells 4+","explanation": "In forward typing, a 1+ reaction with anti-B is suspicious because of the weak reaction and the normal reverse grouping that appears to be group A. This may be indicative of an acquired antigen. In the case of an acquired B antigen, the reverse grouping is the same for a group A person. Choice A is indicative of group AB; choice B is indicative of a group A who may be immunocompromised. Choice D may be caused by a mistyping or an antibody against antigens on reverse cells."},"question": "Which typing results are most likely to occur when a patient has an acquired B antigen?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize problems/ABO discrepancy/2"},{"choices": ["A1B", "A2", "B", "A1"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "A1B","explanation": "The A1B blood group has the least amount of H antigen. This occurs because both A and B epitopes are present on RBCs, compromising the availability of H epitopes. A1B cells will yield weak reactions with anti-H lectin."},"question": "Which blood group has the least amount of H antigen?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological principles/ABO/1"},{"choices": ["A only", "A or O", "B", "AB"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "A or O","explanation": "A person who is in need of RBC transfusion and is an A2 with anti-A1 can be transfused with A or O cells because the anti-A1 is typically only reactive at room temperature."},"question": "What type RBCs can be transfused to an A2 person with anti-A1?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological principles/ABO/3"},{"choices": ["Wash the cells with warm saline, and autoadsorb the serum at 4°C","Retype the sample using a different lot number of reagents","Use polyclonal typing reagents","Report the sample as group AB"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Wash the cells with warm saline, and autoadsorb the serum at 4°C","explanation": "These results point to a cold autoantibody. Washing the cells with warm saline may elute the autoantibody, allowing a valid forward type to be performed. The serum should be adsorbed using washed cells until the autocontrol is negative. Then, the adsorbed serum should be used for reverse typing."},"question": "What should be done if all forward and reverse ABO results as well as the autocontrol are positive?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory and clinical data to specify additional tests/RBCs/ABO discrepancy/3"},{"choices": ["Perform additional testing, such as typing with anti-A1 lectin and anti-A,B","Incubate at 22°C or 4°C to enhance weak expression","Repeat the test with new reagents","Run an antibody identification panel"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Incubate at 22°C or 4°C to enhance weak expression","explanation": "All negative results may be caused by weakened antigens or antibodies. Room temperature or lower incubation temperature may enhance expression of weakened antigens or antibodies."},"question": "What should be done if all forward and reverse ABO results are negative?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory and clinical data to specify additional tests/RBCs/ABO discrepancy/3"},{"choices": ["Arachis hypogaea","Salvia sclarea","Dolichos biflorus","Ulex europeaus"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Dolichos biflorus","explanation": "The immunodominant sugar N-acetyl-galactosamine confers A antigen specificity when present at the terminus of the type 2 precursor chain on the RBC membrane. Therefore, its presence would cause RBCs to react with anti-A1 lectin, Dolichos biflorus."},"question": "N-acetyl-D-galactosamine is the immunodominant carbohydrate that reacts with:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological principles/ABO/2"},{"choices": ["Viral infection","Alloantibodies","Immunodeficiency","Autoimmune hemolytic anemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Immunodeficiency","explanation": "The transplant recipient is probably taking immunosuppressive medication to increase graft survival. This can contribute to the loss of normal blood group antibodies as well as other types of antibodies."},"question": "A stem cell transplant recipient was retyped when she was transferred from another hospital. What is the most likely cause of the following results? Patient cells: Anti-A, neg Anti-B, 4+ Patient serum: A1 cells, neg B cells, neg","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/ABO discrepancy/3"},{"choices": ["Positive reaction with anti-A1 lectin","Positive reaction with A1 cells","Equal reaction with anti-H","Positive reaction with anti-A,B"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Positive reaction with anti-A,B","explanation": "Anti-A,B should react positively with group A or B and any subgroup of A or B (with exception of Am). An A1 (not A2) would react with anti-A1 lectin; only an A2 person with anti-A1 would give a positive reaction with A1 cells; an A2 would react more strongly with anti-H than A1."},"question": "What reaction would be the same for an A1 and an A2 person?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/ABO discrepancy/2"},{"choices": ["Hypogammaglobulinemia","Alloantibody in patient serum","Acquired B","Weak subgroup"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Alloantibody in patient serum","explanation": "The patient is most likely an AB person who has formed a cold-reacting alloantibody reacting with B cells and O cells. An identification panel should be performed. An acquired B person or someone with hypogammaglobulinemia should not make antibody that would agglutinate O cells."},"question": "A female patient at 28 weeks’ pregnancy yields the following results: Patient cells: Anti-A, 3+ Anti-B, 4+ Patient serum: A1 cells, neg B cells, 1+ O cells, 1+ Which of the following could be causing the ABO discrepancy?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/ABO discrepancy/3"},{"choices": ["Immunodeficiency","Masking of antigens by the presence of massive amounts of antibody","Weak or excessive antigen(s)","Impossible to determine"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Weak or excessive antigen(s)","explanation": "Excessive A substance, as may be found in some types of tumors, may be neutralizing anti-A. Weak A subgroups may fail to react with anti-A and require additional testing techniques (e.g., room-temperature incubation) before their expression is apparent."},"question": "Which condition would most likely be responsible for the following typing results? Patient cells: Anti-A, neg Anti-B, neg Patient serum: A1 cells, neg B cells, 4+","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/ABO discrepancy/3"},{"choices": ["Negative B cells","Positive reaction with anti-B","Negative A1 cells","No problem with this typing"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Negative A1 cells","explanation": "The reverse typing should agree with the forward typing in this result. The 4+ reaction with anti-B indicates group B. A positive reaction is expected with A1 cells in the reverse group."},"question": "Which of the following results is most likely discrepant? Anti-A, neg Anti-B, 4+ A1 cells, neg B cells, neg","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/ABO discrepancy/3"},{"choices": ["O positive","B positive","A positive","Undetermined"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Undetermined","explanation": "In a transplantation scenario, there are no methods to employ to solve the discrepancy. The medical laboratory scientist must rely on the patient history of donor type and recipient type and the present serological picture. Giving a B-positive recipient an O-positive transplant constitutes a minor ABO mismatch. The forward type resembles the donor. The reverse type still resembles the recipient. The ABO type reported out does not fit a pattern resulting in an undetermined type."},"question": "A 61-year-old male with a history of multiple myeloma underwent stem cell transplantation 3 years ago. The donor was O positive, and the recipient was B positive. The patient is admitted to a community hospital for fatigue and nausea. Typing results reveal the following: Anti-A = 0 Anti-B =0 Anti-A,B = 0 Anti-D = 4+ A1 cells = 4+ B cells = 0 How would you report this type?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize problems/ABO discrepancy/3"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "ABO Blood Group System"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}